

Akshay Chakrapani

Date of birth: 24/04/1995 | **Nationality:** Indian | **Gender:** Male | **Phone number:**

(+39) 3473104057 (Mobile) | Email address: akkinulaacc@gmail.com | LinkedIn:

www.linkedin.com/in/akshay-chakrapani-757042166 | Instagram:

https://www.instagram.com/krrompir/

Address: Via Mario Pettenghi, 5, 27100, Pavia, Italy (Home)

ABOUT ME

As an R&D Automation Software Engineer, I specialize in crafting and implementing advanced if not simple automation systems. My skill set includes PLC programming, HMI design, and creating customized software solutions for both industrial and research environments. I'm passionate about building intuitive interfaces and enhancing control systems to boost functionality and efficiency.

I'm driven by innovation, constantly working on developing reliable automation frameworks and designing smooth human-machine interfaces to simplify complex operations. Whether it's writing tailored code or configuring PLCs, I'm dedicated to advancing automation technology through ongoing learning and creative problem-solving

WORK EXPERIENCE

05/09/2022 - CURRENT Milan, Italy

R&D AUTOMATION SW ENGINEER ALASCOM S.R.L

- Programming of PLC with versatile languages like Ladder logic and Structured Control Language (SCL)
- Programming of **HMI** with various suppliers (Siemens, Schneider, Proface, Weintek)
- **Node- RED** with which we can custom make our own interface for communication with the PLC or other devices with a common communication protocol like MODBUS TCP or PROFINET
- Designing front end with Node- RED by using **UIBuilder** for much more easier communication with the backend components like industrial devices
- Designing web interfaces using traditional **Vanilla Javascript** (HTML, CSS included) and familiar with **React** Library
- Possibility of seamless communication of **PLC** with **Python**
- Getting more accustomed with **GUI** libraries of Python for future aspects of designing and communication
- Communication of PLC with the Collaboration robots like JAKA by using Python directly or by using PLC such as from Schneider
- Setting up MQTT broker and enabling communication with Node- Red
- MQTT communication with raspberry pi 5, and with existing tools to tunnel the host IP on the cloud to be able to access it anywhere [Port forwarding]
- Focusing on making a custom reverse proxy using NGINX

01/09/2017 - 28/02/2019 Bengaluru, India

AUTOMATION ENGINEER BUHLER INDIA PVT LTD

Buhler India PVT Ltd is a Multi National Company which manufactures food procession machines.

- I started to work as a **GET (Graduate Engineer Trainee)** after my graduation from Bachelors in Mechatronics Engineering.
- I worked in various departments of the company, learning the ways of how an industry works and the interdependence of departments in the company
- I was entitled to many aspects of **Lean Manufacturing** with many quality assessment tools while being trained in the manufacturing department
- Focused in the Automation department where I was designated to **program** the **motors** and **sensors** for the machines which were manufactured in the company, **IO testing of the control panels** before the machines were dispatched to the customers site

01/05/2017 - 30/07/2017 Bengaluru, India

INTERNSHIP HINDUSTAN AERONAUTICS LIMITED

Knowing the complexity in the functioning of a Helicopter, I pursued Internship program in **servicing of a Helicopter** and understanding the functional components of a Helicopter

INTERNSHIP ROBERT BOSCH ELECTRICAL DRIVES INDIA PVT LTD

I took the Internship Program in **Robert Bosch** as a part of my final year project of my Bachelors in Mechatronics Engineering.

I was focused upon quality control in the manufacturing department and solving a problem at that time concerning ball bearings in the steering wheel of cars

8D methodology was the process improvement tool used in solving the problem

EDUCATION AND TRAINING

01/10/2019 - 15/03/2023 Pavia,, Italy

MASTERS IN INDUSTRIAL AUTOMATION AND ROBOTICS University of Pavia

Address Via Adolfo Ferrata, 5, 27100, Pavia,, Italy | Website https://web.unipv.it/

Bengaluru, India

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE- MECHATRONICS ENGINEERING The Oxford College of Engineering

Address 10th Milestone, Hosur Road, Bommanahalli, 560068, Bengaluru, India | Website http://www.theoxford.edu/engineering/

LANGUAGE SKILLS

Mother tongue(s): KANNADA

Other language(s):

	UNDERSTANDING		SPEAKING		WRITING
	Listening	Reading	Spoken production Spoken interaction		
ENGLISH	C2	C2	C2	C2	C2
HINDI	C1	B2	B2	B2	B2
ITALIAN	A2	A2	A1	A1	A1

Levels: A1 and A2: Basic user; B1 and B2: Independent user; C1 and C2: Proficient user

DIGITAL SKILLS

PLC Programming | HMI | SCADA | Siemens TIA PORTAL | Schneider Electric | HMI (Proface, Schneider, Siemens) | Weinktek HMI | NODE red | Html+CSS+JS | React | Python | TKinter (GUI) | PySide6 (GUI) | MATLAB | Simulink | AutoCAD | JAKA | Mqtt Protocol | Eclipse Mosquitto MQTT Broker | NGROK | Nginx | RASPBERRY Pi

HOBBIES

Personal Interests

- Sketching
- Digital Art
- Cooking
- Travelling
- Outdoor games(Cricket, Football, Volleyball)